So first, if you look at the level of wealth inequality, this is the share of total wealth going to the top 10 percent of wealth holders, so you can see the same kind of reversal between the U.S. and Europe that we had before for income inequality. So wealth concentration was higher in Europe than in the U.S. a century ago, and now it is the opposite. But you can also show two things: First, the general level of wealth inequality is always higher than income inequality. So remember, for income inequality, the share going to the top 10 percent was between 30 and 50 percent of total income, whereas for wealth, the share is always between 60 and 90 percent. Okay, so that's fact number one, and that's very important for what follows. Wealth concentration is always a lot higher than income concentration. Fact number two is that the rise in wealth inequality in recent decades is still not enough to get us back to 1910. So the big difference today, wealth inequality is still very large, with 60, 70 percent of total wealth for the top 10, but the good news is that it's actually better than one century ago, where you had 90 percent in Europe going to the top 10. So today what you have is what I call the middle 40 percent, the people who are not in the top 10 and who are not in the bottom 50, and what you can view as the wealth middle class that owns 20 to 30 percent of total wealth, national wealth, whereas they used to be poor, a century ago, when there was basically no wealth middle class. So this is an important change, and it's interesting to see that wealth inequality has not fully recovered to pre-World War I levels, although the total quantity of wealth has recovered. Okay? So this is the total value of wealth relative to income, and you can see that in particular in Europe, we are almost back to the pre-World War I level. So there are really two different parts of the story here. One has to do with the total quantity of wealth that we accumulate, and there is nothing bad per se, of course, in accumulating a lot of wealth, and in particular if it is more diffuse and less concentrated. So what we really want to focus on is the long-run evolution of wealth inequality, and what's going to happen in the future. How can we account for the fact that until World War I, wealth inequality was so high and, if anything, was rising to even higher levels, and how can we think about the future? So let me come to some of the explanations and speculations about the future. Let me first say that probably the best model to explain why wealth is so much more concentrated than income is a dynamic, dynastic model where individuals have a long horizon and accumulate wealth for all sorts of reasons. If people were accumulating wealth only for life cycle reasons, you know, to be able to consume when they are old, then the level of wealth inequality should be more or less in line with the level of income inequality. But it will be very difficult to explain why you have so much more wealth inequality than income inequality with a pure life cycle model, so you need a story where people also care about wealth accumulation for other reasons. So typically, they want to transmit wealth to the next generation, to their children, or sometimes they want to accumulate wealth because of the prestige, the power that goes with wealth. So there must be other reasons for accumulating wealth than just life cycle to explain what we see in the data. Now, in a large class of dynamic models of wealth accumulation with such dynastic motive for accumulating wealth, you will have all sorts of random, multiplicative shocks. So for instance, some families have a very large number of children, so the wealth will be divided. Some families have fewer children. You also have shocks to rates of return. Some families make huge capital gains. Some made bad investments. So you will always have some mobility in the wealth process. Some people will move up, some people will move down. The important point is that, in any such model, for a given variance of such shocks, the equilibrium level of wealth inequality will be a steeply rising function of r minus g. And intuitively, the reason why the difference between the rate of return to wealth and the growth rate is important is that initial wealth inequalities will be amplified at a faster pace with a bigger r minus g. So take a simple example, with r equals five percent and g equals one percent, wealth holders only need to reinvest one fifth of their capital income to ensure that their wealth rises as fast as the size of the economy. So this makes it easier to build and perpetuate large fortunes because you can consume four fifths, assuming zero tax, and you can just reinvest one fifth. So of course some families will consume more than that, some will consume less, so there will be some mobility in the distribution, but on average, they only need to reinvest one fifth, so this allows high wealth inequalities to be sustained. Now, you should not be surprised by the statement that r can be bigger than g forever, because, in fact, this is what happened during most of the history of mankind. And this was in a way very obvious to everybody for a simple reason, which is that growth was close to zero percent during most of the history of mankind. Growth was maybe 0.1, 0.2, 0.3 percent, but very slow growth of population and output per capita, whereas the rate of return on capital of course was not zero percent. It was, for land assets, which was the traditional form of assets in preindustrial societies, it was typically five percent. Any reader of Jane Austen would know that. If you want an annual income of 1,000 pounds, you should have a capital value of 20,000 pounds so that five percent of 20,000 is 1,000. And in a way, this was the very foundation of society, because r bigger than g was what allowed holders of wealth and assets to live off their capital income and to do something else in life than just to care about their own survival. Now, one important conclusion of my historical research is that modern industrial growth did not change this basic fact as much as one might have expected. Of course, the growth rate following the Industrial Revolution rose, typically from zero to one to two percent, but at the same time, the rate of return to capital also rose so that the gap between the two did not really change. So during the 20th century, you had a very unique combination of events. First, a very low rate of return due to the 1914 and 1945 war shocks, destruction of wealth, inflation, bankruptcy during the Great Depression, and all of this reduced the private rate of return to wealth to unusually low levels between 1914 and 1945. And then, in the postwar period, you had unusually high growth rate, partly due to the reconstruction. You know, in Germany, in France, in Japan, you had five percent growth rate between 1950 and 1980 largely due to reconstruction, and also due to very large demographic growth, the Baby Boom Cohort effect. Now, apparently that's not going to last for very long, or at least the population growth is supposed to decline in the future, and the best projections we have is that the long-run growth is going to be closer to one to two percent rather than four to five percent. So if you look at this, these are the best estimates we have of world GDP growth and rate of return on capital, average rates of return on capital, so you can see that during most of the history of mankind, the growth rate was very small, much lower than the rate of return, and then during the 20th century, it is really the population growth, very high in the postwar period, and the reconstruction process that brought growth to a smaller gap with the rate of return. Here I use the United Nations population projections, so of course they are uncertain. It could be that we all start having a lot of children in the future, and the growth rates are going to be higher, but from now on, these are the best projections we have, and this will make global growth decline and the gap between the rate of return go up. Now, the other unusual event during the 20th century was, as I said, destruction, taxation of capital, so this is the pre-tax rate of return. This is the after-tax rate of return, and after destruction, and this is what brought the average rate of return after tax, after destruction, below the growth rate during a long time period. But without the destruction, without the taxation, this would not have happened. So let me say that the balance between returns on capital and growth depends on many different factors that are very difficult to predict: technology and the development of capital-intensive techniques. So right now, the most capital-intensive sectors in the economy are the real estate sector, housing, the energy sector, but it could be in the future that we have a lot more robots in a number of sectors and that this would be a bigger share of the total capital stock that it is today. Well, we are very far from this, and from now, what's going on in the real estate sector, the energy sector, is much more important for the total capital stock and capital share. The other important issue is that there are scale effects in portfolio management, together with financial complexity, financial deregulation, that make it easier to get higher rates of return for a large portfolio, and this seems to be particularly strong for billionaires, large capital endowments. Just to give you one example, this comes from the Forbes billionaire rankings over the 1987-2013 period, and you can see the very top wealth holders have been going up at six, seven percent per year in real terms above inflation, whereas average income in the world, average wealth in the world, have increased at only two percent per year. And you find the same for large university endowments — the bigger the initial endowments, the bigger the rate of return. Now, what could be done? The first thing is that I think we need more financial transparency. We know too little about global wealth dynamics, so we need international transmission of bank information. We need a global registry of financial assets, more coordination on wealth taxation, and even wealth tax with a small tax rate will be a way to produce information so that then we can adapt our policies to whatever we observe. And to some extent, the fight against tax havens and automatic transmission of information is pushing us in this direction. Now, there are other ways to redistribute wealth, which it can be tempting to use. Inflation: it's much easier to print money than to write a tax code, so that's very tempting, but sometimes you don't know what you do with the money. This is a problem. Expropriation is very tempting. Just when you feel some people get too wealthy, you just expropriate them. But this is not a very efficient way to organize a regulation of wealth dynamics. So war is an even less efficient way, so I tend to prefer progressive taxation, but of course, history — (Laughter) — history will invent its own best ways, and it will probably involve a combination of all of these. Thank you. (Applause) Bruno Giussani: Thomas Piketty. Thank you. Thomas, I want to ask you two or three questions, because it's impressive how you're in command of your data, of course, but basically what you suggest is growing wealth concentration is kind of a natural tendency of capitalism, and if we leave it to its own devices, it may threaten the system itself, so you're suggesting that we need to act to implement policies that redistribute wealth, including the ones we just saw: progressive taxation, etc. In the current political context, how realistic are those? How likely do you think that it is that they will be implemented? Thomas Piketty: Well, you know, I think if you look back through time, the history of income, wealth and taxation is full of surprise. So I am not terribly impressed by those who know in advance what will or will not happen. I think one century ago, many people would have said that progressive income taxation would never happen and then it happened. And even five years ago, many people would have said that bank secrecy will be with us forever in Switzerland, that Switzerland was too powerful for the rest of the world, and then suddenly it took a few U.S. sanctions against Swiss banks for a big change to happen, and now we are moving toward more financial transparency. So I think it's not that difficult to better coordinate politically. We are going to have a treaty with half of the world GDP around the table with the U.S. and the European Union, so if half of the world GDP is not enough to make progress on financial transparency and minimal tax for multinational corporate profits, what does it take? So I think these are not technical difficulties. I think we can make progress if we have a more pragmatic approach to these questions and we have the proper sanctions on those who benefit from financial opacity. BG: One of the arguments against your point of view is that economic inequality is not only a feature of capitalism but is actually one of its engines. So we take measures to lower inequality, and at the same time we lower growth, potentially. What do you answer to that? TP: Yeah, I think inequality is not a problem per se. I think inequality up to a point can actually be useful for innovation and growth. The problem is, it's a question of degree. When inequality gets too extreme, then it becomes useless for growth and it can even become bad because it tends to lead to high perpetuation of inequality over time and low mobility. And for instance, the kind of wealth concentrations that we had in the 19th century and pretty much until World War I in every European country was, I think, not useful for growth. This was destroyed by a combination of tragic events and policy changes, and this did not prevent growth from happening. And also, extreme inequality can be bad for our democratic institutions if it creates very unequal access to political voice, and the influence of private money in U.S. politics, I think, is a matter of concern right now. So we don't want to return to that kind of extreme, pre-World War I inequality. Having a decent share of the national wealth for the middle class is not bad for growth. It is actually useful both for equity and efficiency reasons. BG: I said at the beginning that your book has been criticized. Some of your data has been criticized. Some of your choice of data sets has been criticized. You have been accused of cherry-picking data to make your case. What do you answer to that? TP: Well, I answer that I am very happy that this book is stimulating debate. This is part of what it is intended for. Look, the reason why I put all the data online with all of the detailed computation is so that we can have an open and transparent debate about this. So I have responded point by point to every concern. Let me say that if I was to rewrite the book today, I would actually conclude that the rise in wealth inequality, particularly in the United States, has been actually higher than what I report in my book. There is a recent study by Saez and Zucman showing, with new data which I didn't have at the time of the book, that wealth concentration in the U.S. has risen even more than what I report. And there will be other data in the future. Some of it will go in different directions. Look, we put online almost every week new, updated series on the World Top Income Database and we will keep doing so in the future, in particular in emerging countries, and I welcome all of those who want to contribute to this data collection process. In fact, I certainly agree that there is not enough transparency about wealth dynamics, and a good way to have better data would be to have a wealth tax with a small tax rate to begin with so that we can all agree about this important evolution and adapt our policies to whatever we observe. So taxation is a source of knowledge, and that's what we need the most right now. BG: Thomas Piketty, merci beaucoup. Thank you. TP: Thank you. (Applause)
D'abord, si vous regardez la distribution du patrimoine, c'est-à-dire la part du patrimoine total détenue par les 10 % les plus riches, vous observez la même distribution entre l'Europe et les USA que celle que nous avions avant pour les revenus. La concentration de patrimoine était plus élevée en Europe qu'aux USA il y a un siècle, et aujourd'hui c'est le contraire. Mais deux autres choses apparaissent : primo, la distribution du patrimoine est toujours plus inégale que celle des revenus. Rappelez-vous, pour la distribution des revenus la part attribuée aux 10% les plus riches était de 30 à 50% du revenu total, tandis que pour la distribution du patrimoine cette part est toujours comprise entre 60 et 90% du patrimoine total. C'est donc le premier fait et il est décisif pour la suite. La concentration du patrimoine est bien supérieure à celle des revenus. Le deuxième fait est l'augmentation des différences dans la distribution des richesses dans les dernières décennies, à un niveau qui reste inférieur à 1910. Aujourd'hui la distribution du patrimoine est toujours très inégale avec 60 à 70% du patrimoine pour les 10% les plus riches, mais la bonne nouvelle est que c'est mieux qu'il y a un siècle, où 90% du patrimoine en Europe était aux mains de 10% de la population. Aujourd'hui, nous avons ce que j'appelle les « 40% du milieu », ceux qui ne sont ni les 10% les plus riches ni dans les 50% les moins riches, ceux que l'on peut appeler la « classe moyenne », qui possède 20 à 30% du patrimoine national total, alors que cette catégorie était pauvre, il y a 100 ans, quand il n'y avait pour ainsi dire pas de classe moyenne. C'est un changement important et il est intéressant de constater que la distribution du patrimoine n'est pas revenue à son niveau d'avant la 1ère Guerre Mondiale, alors que c'est le cas pour la distribution du patrimoine. Voici la valeur de la richesse venant des revenus, et on observe, particulièrement en Europe, qu'on revient quasiment à des niveaux d'avant la Première Guerre Mondiale. On a donc deux parties distinctes de la même histoire. La première a à voir avec la quantité de patrimoine que nous épargnons et cela n'a rien de mauvais en soi, d'accumuler énormément de richesses, surtout si elles sont bien réparties et peu concentrées. Concentrons-nous sur l'évolution, sur le long terme, de la distribution du patrimoine et sur ce qui risque d'arriver dans le futur. Comment expliquer que, jusqu'en 1914, l'inégalité de répartition du patrimoine ait été aussi forte, et ait pu progresser à des niveaux encore plus élevés ? Quelles conclusions peut-on en tirer pour le futur ? Passons maintenant aux explications et aux hypothèses pour le futur. J'aimerais d'abord souligner que le meilleur modèle pour expliquer pourquoi les patrimoines sont plus concentrés que les revenus est sans doute un modèle dynastique où les individus réfléchissent à long terme et accumulent du patrimoine pour toutes sortes de raisons. Si les gens n'accumulaient ce patrimoine que pour en profiter au cours de leur vie pour pouvoir consommer alors une fois âgées, la distribution du patrimoine devrait alors etre plus ou moins en ligne avec la distribution des revenus. Il est difficile d'expliquer en quoi la distribution du patrimoine est plus inégale que celle des revenus avec un tel modèle. On doit donc envisager un scénario où les gens accumulent du patrimoine pour d'autres raisons. Typiquement, ils veulent transmettre leur patrimoine à la génération suivante, à leurs enfants, ou bien ils veulent accumuler ce patrimoine pour le prestige, ou le pouvoir qu'il procure. Il y a donc d'autres raisons que le cycle de la vie pour pousser à accumuler du patrimoine et expliquer ces chiffres. Dans un grand nombre de modèles dynamiques d'accumulation de patrimoine comprenant la motivation dynastique pour justifier l'accumulation, on trouve toutes sortes de chocs aléatoires multiplicatifs. Par exemple, certaines familles ont beaucoup d'enfants, ce qui divise le patrimoine total. D'autres familles ont moins d'enfants. Il y a aussi des baisses de rendement. Certaines familles font d'énormes profits, d'autres de mauvais investissements. Le processus de création de richesses connaît ainsi des aléas dûs à ces chocs. Certains montent dans la hiérarchie, d'autres reculent. Le point important est que dans un tel modèle, et pour une répartition donnée de tels chocs, le niveau d'équilibre de la distribution de richesse est une fonction croissante de r - g. Intuitivement, la raison pour laquelle la différence entre le rendement du patrimoine et la croissance est si importante est que la distribution du patrimoine de départ s'est amplifiée rapidement à cause d'une différence croissante entre r et g. Prenons un exemple simple, avec un r de 5% et un g de 1%, les détenteurs de patrimoine ne doivent réinvestir que 20% de leurs revenus de capital pour s'assurer que leur patrimoine augmente aussi vite que l'économie. Il est donc plus facile de construire et perpétuer d'énormes fortunes, car dans un scénario sans taxe, vous pouvez en consommer 80% et n'en réinvestir que 20%. Bien sûr certaines familles consommeront plus, d'autres moins, ce qui entraîne une variation de la distribution, mais en moyenne, il leur suffit de réinvestir 20% pour maintenir les inégalités de patrimoines. Il ne faut pas être supris par le fait que r peut rester indéfiniment supérieur à g car c'est ce qui s'est passé durant la plus grande part de notre histoire et c'était assez évident pour tout le monde, simplement car la croissance est restée quasiment nulle durant la majeure partie de l'histoire. La croissance était de l'ordre de 0,1, 0,2 ou 0,3%, avec une faible croissance démographique et une faible productivité par habitant, alors que le taux de rendement du capital restait bien sûr supérieur à 0. Dans le cas des terres, qui étaient la forme classique de capital dans les sociétés préindustrielles, le rendement était typiquement de 5%. Quiconque a lu Jane Austen sait ça. Si vous vouliez 1000 livres de revenus annuels, il vous fallait un capital de 20 000 livres de sorte que 5% de 20 000 vous donnent 1 000 en retour. D'une certaine manière, c'était un des fondements de la société, car le fait que r soit supérieur à g permettait aux détenteurs de capitaux et de patrimoine de vivre des revenus de leurs capitaux et de faire autre chose de leurs vies, que de se battre quotidiennement pour survivre. En fait, une des conclusions principales de mes recherches historiques est que la croissance industrielle moderne n'a étonnamment pas changé grand chose à cette situation. Bien sûr, le taux de croissance qui a suivi la Révolution Industrielle a augmenté, passant de 0 à 1 ou 2%, mais dans le même temps, le taux de rendement du capital a également augmenté de telle sorte que l'écart entre les deux n'a pas fondamentalement changé. On a pu observer durant le 20ème siècle une combinaison inédite d'événements. D'abord, un taux de rendement faible dû aux chocs qu'ont été les deux guerres mondiales, la destruction de la croissance, l'inflation, ou faillites lors de la Grande Dépression, tout cela a conduit à un taux de rendement des patrimoines privés à un niveau inhabituellement bas entre 1914 et 1945. Ensuite, après la guerre, on a connu une croissance inhabituellement forte, due, entre autre, à la reconstruction. L' Allemagne, la France, le Japon ont connu des taux de croissance de 5% entre 1950 et 1980, grâce à la reconstruction, et aussi à une forte croissance démographique, le fameux « Baby Boom ». Mais cela ne devrait pas durer très longtemps, la croissance démographique devrait baisser dans le futur, et les meilleurs scénarios prévoient une croissance à long terme plus proche de 1 à 2% que de 4 ou 5%. En examinant ces graphiques, qui sont les meilleures estimations en notre possession sur la croissance du PIB mondial et le rendement du capital, le rendement moyen du capital, on remarque un taux de croissance très faible sur des longues durées, bien en dessous du rendement du capital puis au cours du 20ème siècle une croissance démographique exceptionnelle après 1945, et l'effet de la reconstruction, qui ont réduit l'écart entre taux de croissance (g) et de rendement (r). J'utilise ici les projections démographiques des Nations-Unies, qui sont bien sûr incertaines. Nous pourrions très bien avoir beaucoup d'enfants dans le futur ce qui augmenterait le taux de croissance, mais aujourd'hui ce sont les meilleures projections dont nous disposons, et cela ralentira la croissance et poussera l'écart avec le taux de retour sur investissement à la hausse. L'autre événement inhabituel qui a eu lieu au 20ème siècle a été, comme je l'ai souligné, la destruction du capital et sa taxation, ce que vous voyez est donc un rendement avant taxation. Voici donc ce même rendement du capital après taxation, et après sa destruction, et c'est la raison qui a conduit à un rendement moyen de capital après taxes et destruction, plus faible que la croissance pendant une longue période. Mais sans cette destruction, sans la taxation, cela n'aurait jamais eu lieu. Il faut bien voir que cet écart entre le taux de rendement du capital et la croissance dépend de nombreux facteurs très difficiles à prédire : la technologie et le développement de techniques à forte intensité capitalistique. Aujourd'hui, les secteurs de l'économie à plus forte intensité capitalistique sont l'immobilier, le logement et l'énergie, mais dans l'avenir nous pourrions voir plus de robots dans d'autres secteurs, ce qui augmenterait de facto la part du stock de capital dans ces secteurs. Bien sûr, on en est encore loin, et pour l'instant, ce qui se passe dans l'immobilier et l'énergie est bien plus important pour la valorisation des entreprises. L'autre facteur important est qu'il existe des effets d'échelle dans la gestion de portefeuilles associés à une complexité financière, une dérégulation de la finance, qui assurent plus facilement des rendements importants pour un portefeuille étendu, et cela semble particulièrement le cas pour les milliardaires ou les fonds de pension. Pour vous donner un exemple, si l'on regarde le classement Forbes des milliardaires sur la période 1987-2013, on s'aperçoit que les fortunes des personnalités les plus riches ont crû à raison de 6 ou 7% par an au dessus de l'inflation, pendant que le revenu moyen et le patrimoine moyen ont seulement crû de 2% par an dans le monde. Et l'on observe le même effet pour les fonds d'investissement universitaires plus la dotation initiale est grande, plus le rendement sera élevé. Maintenant, que peut-on faire ? Avant tout nous avons besoin de plus de transparence financière. On ne connaît pas suffisamment les dynamiques de la richesse mondiale, il faut donc plus d'échanges internationaux d'informations bancaires. Nous avons besoin d'un registre global des patrimoines, d'une meilleure coordination des politiques fiscales et même une faible taxation du patrimoine serait une piste pour produire de l'information permettant d'adapter nos politiques publiques à la réalité des faits. D'une certaine manière, la lutte contre les paradis fiscaux et l'échange automatique d'informations nous poussent déjà dans cette direction. Ceci dit, il existe d'autres manières de redistribuer les richesses qui peuvent séduire. D'abord, l'inflation : il est plus facile d'imprimer des billets que de rédiger un code fiscal, mais il est parfois difficile de savoir comment utiliser l'argent. Ce qui pose problème. L'expropriation a également de quoi séduire, quand quelqu'un est trop riche, on lui confisque ses biens. Mais ce n'est pas une méthode très efficace pour réguler la dynamique des richesses. La guerre est encore moins efficace, j'ai donc tendance à préférer la taxation progressive, mais, évidemment, l'Histoire (Rires) trouvera de meilleures méthodes, ce qui impliquera probablement une combinaison de tout ceci. Merci. (Applaudissements) Bruno Giussani : Thomas Piketty, merci. J'aimerais vous poser 2 ou 3 questions parce que votre maîtrise des données m'impressionne, bien sûr, mais en fait, ce que vous suggérez est que la concentration croissante du patrimoine est une tendance naturelle du capitalisme, et si rien n'est fait pour le réguler, cela pourrait menacer l'ensemble du système. Vous suggérez donc d'agir et de mettre en place des politiques pour redistribuer la richesse, comme celles que nous venons juste de voir : taxation progressive, etc. Dans le contexte politique actuel, est-ce réaliste ? Pensez-vous qu'on puisse vraiment espérer les voir un jour mises en place ? T. Piketty : Vous savez, si on remonte assez loin, l'histoire du revenu, du patrimoine et des taxes, est pleine de surprises. Je ne suis pas impressionné par ceux qui savent à l'avance ce qui se passera ou pas. Il y a un siècle, beaucoup de gens vous auraient dit que la taxation progressive du revenu ne serait jamais effective et aujourd'hui elle l'est. Et même il y a cinq ans de cela, nombre de gens auraient dit que le secret bancaire serait éternel en Suisse, que la Suisse était trop forte pour plier à la pression internationale, puis soudain, quelques sanctions américaines contre les banques suisses ont radicalement changé ça et on se dirige maintenant vers plus de transparence financière. Je pense qu'il n'est pas très difficile d'améliorer la coordination des politiques publiques. Nous aurons bientôt un traité qui concernera la moitié du PIB mondial, c'est à dire les USA et l'Europe si cela n'est pas suffisant pour faire des progrès sur la transparence financière et sur une taxation minimale des profits des multinationales, que faut-il alors ? Le problème n'est pas technique. Je pense qu'on fera des progrès si nous adoptons une approche plus pragmatique sur ces questions et des sanctions plus adaptées envers ceux qui bénéficient de cette opacité. B. Giussani : Un des arguments contre votre vision est que l'inégalité économique n'est pas seulement une caractéristique du capitalisme, mais un de ses moteurs. Donc si on prend des mesures pour réduire les inégalités, on risque en même temps de réduire la croissance. Que leur répondez-vous ? T. Piketty : En effet, les inégalités ne sont pas un problème en soi. Elles sont même, d'une manière, utiles pour l'innovation et la croissance Tout le problème concerne le niveau acceptable. Si les inégalités deviennent trop extrêmes, elles ne sont plus utiles pour la croissance et peuvent devenir néfastes car elles entraînent la perpétuation d'inégalités dans le temps et une faible mobilité sociale. Par exemple, le genre de concentration de richesses qu'on a connue au 19e siècle et jusqu'à la Première Guerre Mondiale dans chaque pays d'Europe n'a pas du tout contribué à la croissance. Ces inégalités ont été brisées par une série d'événements tragiques et de changements politiques, et la croissance est revenue. Les inégalités extrêmes peuvent également être néfastes pour nos institutions démocratiques si elles créent des inégalités de représentativité politique et l'influence de l'argent privé sur la politique américaine est, je pense, un réel problème aujourd'hui. Personne n'a donc intérêt à ce qu'on revienne aux niveaux d'inégalités d'avant 1914. Le fait que la classe moyenne ait une part normale de la richesse mondiale n'est pas néfaste pour la croissance. Au contraire, c'est utile pour des raisons d'équité et d'efficacité. B. Giussani : Comme je l'ai dit au début, votre livre a été critiqué. Une part de vos données l'a été. Certains de vos choix de jeu de données également. Vous avez été accusé de ne choisir que les données qui vous arrangeaient. Que répondez-vous ? T. Piketty : Je suis très content de voir le très large débat que ce livre a suscité. C'était un de mes objectifs initiaux. Si j'ai mis en ligne l'ensemble des données avec le détail de mes calculs, c'est pour qu'on puisse avoir un débat ouvert et transparent sur le sujet. J'ai répondu point par point à toutes les objections soulevées. Et si je devais réécrire ce livre, je conclurais que la montée des inégalités de richesses, en particulier aux USA, a été plus forte que celle décrite dans mon livre. Il y a récemment eu une étude de Saez et Zucman qui démontre avec de nouvelles données que je n'avais pas lorsque je l'ai écrit que la concentration de richesses aux USA a crû encore plus que ce que j'ai écrit. Et il y aura d'autres données dans le futur. Certaines iront dans d'autres directions. Vous savez, chaque semaine nous mettons en ligne une mise à jour de la base World Top Income et on continuera à le faire, en particulier pour les pays émergents, et j'invite tous ceux qui peuvent à contribuer à la collecte de ces données. En fait, je suis assez d'accord pour dire qu'il n'y a pas assez de transparence dans la dynamique des richesses, et une bonne manière d'avoir de meilleures données serait d'avoir une taxe sur le patrimoine avec au départ un taux faible pour obtenir un consensus sur l'importance de cette évolution puis adapter nos politiques en fonction des résultats. L'impôt est une source d'information et c'est ce dont nous avons le plus besoin aujourd'hui. B. Giussani : Merci beaucoup. T. Piketty : Merci. (Applaudissements)